A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of the Vice President of Administration, Office Files of Arthur D. Trottenberg FA669
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of the Vice President of Administration, Office Files of Arthur D. Trottenberg
1968-1979
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA669
29.36 Cubic Feet
The office files of Arthur D. Trottenberg document the varied responsibilities Trottenberg fulfilled in his role as Vice President of Administration for the Ford Foundation from 1968 to1979. The files were transferred to the Foundation's Archives in increments spanning the years 1969-1991, and they were formally accessioned all together in 2004. Series have been reworked, but Trottenberg's original filing order (primarily chronological) has been retained. Budget reports and some papers from the Board of Trustees, including the Board's Executive Committee and its Finance Committee, were removed from the collection. These documents are noted in Appendices C and D, and can be found in their respective collections in the Archives. Information on specific program-related investments, as noted in Appendix E, has also been removed from the collection and can be located in the Closed Grant File Room. The Foundation used the services of a number of legal consultants. Written reports from some of these consultants can be found within the collection. However, a number of legal consultants were only evidenced within the collection by the bills they sent to the Foundation, which have been removed from the collection. For a full list of legal consultants, see Appendix F. Access to folders 454-458 in box 46 is restricted; the researcher should consult the archivist before viewing the materials in these folders. The position of Vice President of Administration in the 1970s differed from its present-day counterpart in that it encompassed a wider variety of responsibilities. The former position included the present-day's responsibilities – facilities, information services, purchasing – as well as overseeing the work of the Comptroller's Office, Manpower Services (human resources), and Program-Related Investments. Thus, Trottenberg's files provide the researcher with a broad view of the Foundation's activities during his tenure.
Biographical / Historical
Arthur D. Trottenberg was Vice President of Administration for the Ford Foundation from July 1968 until his retirement in November 1979.
Trottenberg was born December 30, 1917. After serving as a Captain for the United States Air Force (1942-1946), he received his A.B. degree in 1948 from Harvard University. Upon graduating, Trottenberg remained at Harvard until 1968, filling the following positions:
• Manager, Operating Services • Assistant to Vice President • Vice President, Radcliffe College • Assistant Dean, Faculty of Arts and Sciences
In 1979, Trottenberg retired from the Foundation to accept an appointment as the Associate Dean of the faculty of Arts and Sciences at Harvard University.
Throughout his career, Trottenberg was a consultant to the United States Office of Education, as well as to a number of colleges, universities, and foundations. He also served as the director and secretary of the Salzburg Seminar in American Studies until his position at the Foundation required him to resign from those posts in 1968.
Trottenberg authored a number of publications including, A Vision of Paris-Atget and Proust (Macmillan 1963) and various articles on education, architecture, planning, and photography for several journals and magazines.
Arthur D. Trottenberg died in Cambridge, MA on June 20, 2003.
Scope and Contents
The office files of Arthur D. Trottenberg consist of 32 linear feet (64 archival boxes, plus one flat box) of primarily memoranda, correspondence, reports, and policy papers. Policy papers refer to both drafts of policy statements and pages from policy manuals. Other materials found in the collection include telegrams, speeches/statements, press releases, newspaper articles, audits and financial reviews, questionnaires, charts, handwritten notes, photographs, maps, and blueprints. The records document Trottenberg's tenure as the Vice President of Administration at the Ford Foundation, 1968-1979. The files include a limited number of records from before Trottenberg's term with the Foundation. These earlier documents are mostly records passed on to Trottenberg from his predecessor, Verne S. Atwater.
The files cover a wide range of topics that is reflective of Trottenberg's various responsibilities as the Vice President of Administration of the Foundation. Trottenberg oversaw a number of departments – Comptroller's Office, Manpower Services (name changed to Office of Personnel Services in 1973), Logistical Services, and Program-Related Investments – causing his files to serve as a useful cross-section of the Foundation's activities in the 1970s.
Arrangement
The office files of Arthur D. Trottenberg are arranged into 11 series:
Series I: ADMINISTRATION AND OPERATIONS (1964-1980, bulk 1968-1979) Series II: MEMORANDA AND CORRESPONDENCE (1968-1979) Series III: FINANCIAL (1958-1980, bulk 1970-1975) Series IV: PERSONNEL (1958-1980, bulk 1968-1978) Series V: INFORMATION SYSTEMS AND SERVICES (1967-1983, bulk 1967-1977) Series VI: OVERSEAS (1966-1979, bulk 1968-1977) Series VII: PROGRAM ACTIVITY (1958-1979, bulk 1968-1977) Series VIII: SELF STUDY (1955-1979, bulk 1968-1973) Series IX: SUBJECT FILES (1949-1979, bulk 1968-1977) Series X: REAL ESTATE (1966-1979, bulk 1967-1976) Series XI: BOARD OF TRUSTEES (1962-1979, bulk 1967-1978)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Administration and Operations, 1964-1980; 1968-1979; I
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists mainly of memoranda, but also includes correspondence, telegrams, reports, policy papers, speeches/statements, press releases, and newspaper articles.
  Arrangement
  Series I, Administraion and Operations, is housed in ten archival boxes, and is divided into two subseries: Administration and Operations. "Operations" refers to the Foundation's program areas. Within these subseries, the files are arranged hierarchically by division and office. Items within each folder are arranged chronologically, maintaining original order.
  Administration and Operations The Administration and Operations series contains materials from the Foundation's divisions, offices, and staff members. The series consists of various types of material such as reports and policy papers. However, the primary material found in this series is memoranda between Trottenberg and the staff members, demonstrating Trottenberg's role within various areas of the Foundation's work. The series is most abundant in Trottenberg's interaction with McGeorge Bundy, Roger Kennedy, and Howard Dressner, as well as the Office of the Comptroller, and Program-Related Investments. While not as profuse, the series also contains some documentation of the work of others, such as a few folders dedicated to the Division of Education and Research and its program officers. The series covers a wide range of topics spanning the Foundation's activities. Some of the most prominent topics include affirmative action, management costs, tax reporting, program-related investments, grant payments, review of program priorities, self-evaluation and task forces, record-keeping and records management, and benefit plans. This series is best used in conjunction with other series.
  - Administration
    - Office of the President - Bundy, McGeorge, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Office of the President - Bundy, McGeorge, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Office of the President - Bundy, McGeorge, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Office of the President - Bundy, McGeorge, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Office of the President - Bundy, McGeorge, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Office of the President - Bundy, McGeorge, 1974 January-June (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Office of the President - Bundy, McGeorge, 1974 July-December (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Office of the President - Bundy, McGeorge, 1975 January-October (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Office of the President - Bundy, McGeorge, 1975 December (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Office of the President - Bundy, McGeorge, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Office of the President - Bundy, McGeorge, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Office of the President - Smith, Theodore, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Office of the President - Cuninggim, Merrimon, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Office of the President - Cuninggim, Merrimon, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Office of the President - Towers, Perrin, Forster and Crosby, Inc., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Division of Administration, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Division of Administration, 1967-1980 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Division of Administration - Atwater, Verne, 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Division of Administration - Mayer, Robert, 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, general, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, general, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, general, 1970 January-June (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, general, 1970 July-December (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, general, 1971 January-June (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, general, 1971 July-December (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, general, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, general, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, general, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, general, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, general, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, withholding federal income tax, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, withholding federal income tax, 1972-1976 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, taxes, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, taxes, 1971 January-May (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, taxes, 1971 June-December (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, taxes, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, taxes, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, taxes, 1976-1979 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Division of Administration - Comptroller, reports, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Division of Administration - Logistical Services, 1967-1970 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Division of Administration - Purchasing Services, FY 1968 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Division of Administration - Building Services, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Division of Administration - Building Services, use of facilities, 1968-1972 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Division of Administration - Building Services, recycling, 1971-1975 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Division of Administration - Program-Related Investments, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Division of Administration - Program-Related Investments, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Division of Administration - Program-Related Investments, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Division of Administration - Program-Related Investments, 1971 January-June (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Division of Administration - Program-Related Investments, 1971 July-December (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Division of Administration - Program-Related Investments, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Division of Administration - Chafkin, Sol, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Division of Administration - Kelly, Eamon, 1973-1976 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Office of the Secretary – Dressner, Howard, 1968-1971 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Office of the Secretary – Dressner, Howard, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - Office of the Secretary – Dressner, Howard, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Office of the Secretary - Office of General Counsel – Dressner, Howard, 1971-1974 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Office of the Secretary - Office of General Counsel – Dressner, Howard, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Office of the Secretary - Legal Services, 1969-1973 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Vice President for Finance - Kennedy, Roger, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Vice President for Finance - Kennedy, Roger, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Vice President for Finance - Kennedy, Roger, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Vice President for Finance - Kennedy, Roger, 1974 January-June (Box 8, Folder 62)
    - Vice President for Finance - Kennedy, Roger, 1974 September-December (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - Vice President for Finance - Kennedy, Roger, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - Vice President for Finance - Ellis, Reed, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - Vice President for Finance - Treasurer, 1971-1975 (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Vice President for Finance - Lenagh, Thomas, 1969-1972 (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Office of Reports - Office of Reports, 1968-1971 (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - Office of Reports - Office of Reports, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - Office of Reports - Office of Reports, 1974-1977 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - Office of Reports - Annual Report, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 71)
    - Office of Reports - Annual Report, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 72)
  - Operations
    - Division of Humanities and Arts - Lowry, W. McNeil, 1968-1976 (Box 9, Folder 73)
    - Division of Education and Research, 1968-1976 (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - Division of Education and Research - Ward, F. Champion, 1967-1972 (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - Division of Education and Research - Howe, Harold, 1971-1973 (Box 9, Folder 76)
    - Division of Education and Research - Cheit, Earl, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - Division of Education and Research - Ellis, Reed, 1968-1969 (Box 9, Folder 78)
    - Office of Public Broadcasting - Friendly, Fred W. and David Davis, 1970-1973 (Box 9, Folder 79)
    - Division of National Affairs - Sviridoff, Mitchell, 1967-1971 (Box 10, Folder 80)
    - Division of National Affairs - Sviridoff, Mitchell, 1972-1977 (Box 10, Folder 81)
    - Division of National Affairs - Robinson, Marshall, 1973-1979 (Box 10, Folder 82)
    - Division of International Affairs, 1969-1971 (Box 10, Folder 83)
    - Division of International Affairs, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 84)
- Memoranda and Correspondence, 1968-1979; II
  The Memoranda subseries includes Trottenberg's chronological files and other assorted staff memoranda (mostly sent from Trottenberg to the staff, though there are some memoranda that were sent from other staff member to Trottenberg). The Correspondence subseries includes miscellaneous correspondence with people outside of the Foundation. Some correspondence deals with grant proposals. The series consists of primarily memoranda and correspondence, but also includes some telegrams, policy papers, and reports.
  Series II, Memoranda and Correspondence, is housed in seven archival boxes, and is divided into two subseries: Memoranda and Correspondence.
  Memoranda and Correspondence The Memoranda and Correspondence series provides a rough outline of Trottenberg's influence during his post at the Foundation. Even more so than the previous series, the documents in this series touch on topics that span all of the other series in this collection, such as affirmative action, computer usage, library services, access to Foundation records, travel policy, salary policy, medical plan, energy conservation, fellowships, grant payment procedures, leasing office space, and real estate inquiries. Since the topics tend to be mixed together, the files in this series may not be the most useful on their own. They may be better used in conjunction with the other series as a way of filling in holes in the data.
  - Memoranda
    - Staff Memos, 1973 January-August (Box 10, Folder 85)
    - Staff Memos, 1973 September-December (Box 10, Folder 86)
    - Staff Memos, 1974 January-May (Box 10, Folder 87)
    - Staff Memos, 1974 June-December (Box 10, Folder 88)
    - Staff Memos, 1975 January-June (Box 11, Folder 89)
    - Staff Memos, 1975 July-December (Box 11, Folder 90)
    - Staff Memos, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 91)
    - Staff Memos, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 92)
    - Staff Memos, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 93)
    - Chronological Files, 1968 January-June (Box 11, Folder 94)
    - Chronological Files, 1968 July-December (Box 11, Folder 95)
    - Chronological Files, 1969 January-June (Box 11, Folder 96)
    - Chronological Files, 1969 July-December (Box 11, Folder 97)
    - Chronological Files, 1970 January-August (Box 12, Folder 98)
    - Chronological Files, 1970 September-December (Box 12, Folder 99)
    - Chronological Files, 1971 January-June (Box 12, Folder 100)
    - Chronological Files, 1971 July-December (Box 12, Folder 101)
    - Chronological Files, 1972 January-June (Box 12, Folder 102)
    - Chronological Files, 1972 July-December (Box 12, Folder 103)
    - Chronological Files, 1973 January-June (Box 12, Folder 104)
    - Chronological Files, 1973 July-December (Box 12, Folder 105)
    - Chronological Files, 1974 January-June (Box 12, Folder 106)
    - Chronological Files, 1974 July-December (Box 12, Folder 107)
    - Chronological Files, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 108)
    - Chronological Files, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 109)
    - Chronological Files, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 110)
    - Chronological Files, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 111)
    - Chronological Files, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 112)
  - Correspondence
    Items within each folder are mostly arranged chronologically, maintaining original order. However, Trottenberg kept some of his correspondence files in alphabetical order based on the correspondent's last name. Original order has been maintained in these files as well.
    - Correspondence, general, 1970-1979 (Box 13, Folder 113)
    - Correspondence, proposals, 1971-1972 (Box 13, Folder 114)
    - Correspondence, proposals, 1974-1975 (Box 13, Folder 115)
    - Alphabetical Files, A-H, 1968-1969 (Box 14, Folder 116)
    - Alphabetical Files, K-R, 1968-1969 (Box 14, Folder 117)
    - Alphabetical Files, S-Z, 1968-1969 (Box 14, Folder 118)
    - Alphabetical Files, A-L, 1970-1971 (Box 14, Folder 119)
    - Alphabetical Files, Ma-Me, 1970-1971 (Box 14, Folder 120)
    - Alphabetical Files, Mi-Y, 1970-1971 (Box 14, Folder 121)
    - Alphabetical Files, A-F, 1972-1973 (Box 15, Folder 122)
    - Alphabetical Files, G-M, 1972-1973 (Box 15, Folder 123)
    - Alphabetical Files, N-Z, 1972-1973 (Box 15, Folder 124)
    - Alphabetical Files, A-J, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 125)
    - Alphabetical Files, K-Z, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 126)
    - Alphabetical Files, B-J, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 127)
    - Alphabetical Files, K-W, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 128)
    - Alphabetical Files, A-B, 1976-1979 (Box 16, Folder 129)
    - Alphabetical Files, D-O, 1976-1979 (Box 16, Folder 130)
    - Alphabetical Files, P-W, 1976-1979 (Box 16, Folder 131)
- Financial, 1958-1980; 1970-1975; III
  The General subseries consists of documents on a number of topics, such as accounting, management cost actions, and financial reports. The Budget subseries contains budget materials ranging from general management costs to costs of particular offices. The Budget subseries documents budget planning only. The series consists of memoranda, correspondence, reports, charts, and notes.
  Series III, Financial, is housed in seven archival boxes, and is divided into two subseries: General and Budget. Items within each folder are arranged chronologically, maintaining original order.
  Financial The Financial series contains various materials, such as a number of financial reports, both internal and outsourced to consultants. Other topics include, accounting procedures, balance of payments, the General Reserve, and management costs. However, the series is most complete in its documentation of budget planning. Trottenberg was a large presence in the process of forming the annual budgets for all of the Foundation's divisions and offices. His role in budget planning is particularly notable in the early half of the 1970s when the Foundation underwent a period of major retrenchment which will be discussed in more depth later.
  - General
    - Accounting, recentralization, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 132)
    - Accounting, instruction, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 133)
    - Cash Flow, 1970-1977 (Box 16, Folder 134)
    - Balance of Payments, 1965-1969 (Box 16, Folder 135)
    - General Reserves, 1972-1978 (Box 16, Folder 136)
    - Management Costs, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 137)
    - Management Costs, projection, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 138)
    - Management Cost Actions, 1971-1972 (Box 16, Folder 139)
    - Management Cost Actions, 1973-1975 (Box 16, Folder 140)
    - Management Cost Actions, 1976-1978 (Box 17, Folder 141)
    - Future Management Options, 1977-1978 (Box 17, Folder 142)
    - Fiscal Status Report, 1968 (Box 17, Folder 143)
    - Quarterly Financial Reports, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 144)
    - Quarterly Financial Reports, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 145)
    - Quarterly Financial Reports, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 146)
    - Quarterly Financial Reports, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 147)
    - Quarterly Financial Reports, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 148)
    - Quarterly Financial Reports, 1974 (Box 17, Folder 149)
    - Quarterly Financial Reports, 1975 (Box 17, Folder 150)
    - Quarterly Financial Reports, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 151)
    - Quarterly Financial Reports, 1977 (Box 17, Folder 152)
    - Lucas, Tucker, and Company, 1968-1972 (Box 17, Folder 153)
    - Financial Statements, Price Waterhouse & Co., 1958-1960 (Box 17, Folder 154)
    - Financial Statements, Price Waterhouse & Co., 1961-1963 (Box 17, Folder 155)
    - Financial Statements, Price Waterhouse & Co., 1964-1966 (Box 17, Folder 156)
    - Financial Statements, Price Waterhouse & Co., 1967-1969 (Box 17, Folder 157)
    - Financial Statements, Price Waterhouse & Co., 1970-1972 (Box 18, Folder 158)
    - Financial Statements, Price Waterhouse & Co., 1973-1974 (Box 18, Folder 159)
    - Financial Statements, Price Waterhouse & Co., 1975-1976 (Box 18, Folder 160)
    - Financial Statements, Price Waterhouse & Co., 1977-1978 (Box 18, Folder 161)
    - Financial Statements, Price Waterhouse & Co., 1979-1980 (Box 18, Folder 162)
  - Budget
    Separated Materials
    All final reports have been removed from the collection and can be found in the Budget Records (see Appendix C).
    - Budget, general - FY 1970, 1968 November - 1969 December (Box 18, Folder 163)
    - Budget, general - FY 1971, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 164)
    - Budget, general - FY 1972, 1970 October - 1972 December (Box 18, Folder 165)
    - Budget, general - FY 1973, 1972 January - 1973 February (Box 18, Folder 166)
    - Budget, general - FY 1974-1975, 1972 January - February (Box 19, Folder 167)
    - Budget, general - FY 1974-1975, 1972 February - 1974 April (Box 19, Folder 168)
    - Management Budget - FY 1970, 1968 June - 1969 September (Box 19, Folder 169)
    - Management Budget - FY 1970, 1969 December - 1970 December (Box 19, Folder 170)
    - Management Budget - FY 1974-1975, 1973 May - September (Box 19, Folder 171)
    - Management Budget - FY 1974-1975, 1974 February - 1975 December (Box 19, Folder 172)
    - Management Budget - FY 1976-1977, 1975 January - 1977 December (Box 19, Folder 173)